Guide to the Steinbeck - Ainsworth Collection
Department of Special Collections
- Correspondence, Series 1
  - From Jackson J. Benson to Beth 10/20/69-12/31/70, 4 letters, typed, 6 total p. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    About writing JS's biography; lots of questions; includes 1 letter to Mrs. Taylor; San Diego Stage College stationery; with two envelopes; location(s): San Diego
  - From Jackson J. Benson to Beth 6/10/1987, letter, typed, 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Requesting permission to use a photo of Beth and Burgess Meredith; with envelope; location(s): La Mesa, CA
  - From Bob Gamble(?), Dept. of Interior to Beth 3/17/1971, letter, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Thanks for Pacific Grove house tour; location(s): Washington, DC
  - From Stephanie Kraft to Jane Thomson, Valley Guild 12/17/1978, letter, typed, 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Describes Salinas house; location(s): Amherst, MA
  - From Jay Parini to Liz, Beth and Jim 1/16/1992, letter, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Thanks for information; location(s): Middlebury, VT
  - From Robert DeMott to Beth 5/23/1980, letter, typed, 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    With 18-pg. biographical essay about JS; location(s): Athens, OH
- Literary Works, Series 2
  - The Gifts of Iban 1927(?), short story, typed, 12 p. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    The Gifts of Iban; 3400 words; typed original with a few corrections in pencil; location(s): Long Beach, CA
  - I Go Back to Ireland 1/31/1953, article photocopies, 6 p. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    I Go Back to Ireland, Collier's Magazine
  - My War with the Ospreys 3/1/1957, article photocopies, 6 p. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    My War with the Ospreys, Holiday Magazine
  - An Autograph no date, poem or song, typed, 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 27)
    An Autograph
  - In the old days, when men knew that virtue should be rewarded....; no date, song, typed, 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    In the old days, when men knew that virtue should be rewarded...; 4 copies
  - Untitled no date, short story, typed, 13 p. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Untitled story about a young girl and a nymph; carbon copies; many corrections
  - Oyez no date, poem, typed, 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Oyez, Old English poem; carbon copies
  - In June in the month of roses....; 1856?, poem, hand, ink, 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 31)
    In June in the month of roses....; appears to be about JS Sr. marrying into the Hamilton family; very uncertain authorship; possibly 1856; original and two copies
  - East of Eden [1951-1952?], novel proof print, p. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Unrevised proof of East of Eden for The Viking Press.
- Documents and Ephemera, Series 3
  - 2/10/1888, dance card, hand pencil, 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 32)
    With JS Sr. and brothers listed; location(s): Salinas
  - 1923-1924, 3 report cards, hand, ink, 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 33)
    For Spring 1923, Fall 1923, Spring 1924; English major; average grades; Everett W. Smith signature; location(s): Stanford
  - 7/24/28-8/22/28, deed, letter, typed, 6 p. (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Deed and papers relating to purchase of laboratory space; sold for $7000; location(s): Monterey
  - 1939, card, hand, ink, 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Certificate awarded to "Mr. J. Steinbeck, man of letters" for joining the International Society of Creative Intellectuals; location(s): Paris
  - 1940s, envelopes, hand, ink, many p. (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Ed Ricketts' stamp collection; envelopes from Mexico, England, Denmark, etc.
  - 1/1/1941, deed, typed, 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 37)
    Deed to Santa Clara house; two copies; location(s): Santa Clara
  - 1969?, sermon, letter, typed, 5 p. (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Sermon from JS's funeral(?); with a letter from "Doris" to Beth
  - 11/4/69-11/2/72, letters, typed, many p. (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Steinbeck Estate letters relating to Beth
  - 1970s?, flyer, typed, 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Informational flyer about the Steinbeck House, luncheons; location(s): Salinas
  - 1/11/1977, articles, bylaws, typed, 9 p. (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Articles and bylaws of the John Steinbeck Foundation; location(s): Salinas
  - April 1977-3/5/810, 3 articles, 2 letters, typed, 5 p. (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Biographical newspaper articles about JS, with letters
- Photos, Series 4
  - John Adolph Steinbeck family photos no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - John Ernst Steinbeck no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Olive Hamilton Steinbeck no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Photos taken of her alone
  - Olive Hamilton Steinbeck no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Group photos
  - Hamilton Family no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Miscellaneous photos
  - Steinbeck, John and Almira no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 6)
    50th Anniversary Photos
  - Olive and Ernst with grandchildren no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Young pictures and group shots no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - John and Mary with Red Pony no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - John Steinbeck school photos no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - John and Gwyn with Thom (in pool) no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Gwyn and sons no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - John, Elaine and boys in Sag Harbor (boys ~ 4 and 6 years old) no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Thom and John Jr. without parents no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Thom and John Jr. mid teens ca. 1961 1962, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - John Steinbeck Nobel Prize in Stockholm 12/10/1962, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - John Steinbeck Cruises abroad no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - John Steinbeck with Wiltshires in Japan, ca 1967 1967, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - John Steinbeck and John Jr. no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - John Steinbeck- misc. photos as a younger man no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - John Steinbeck- misc. photos as an older man no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - John Steinbeck and Beskov portraits- copies of paintings no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - John Steinbeck and Elaine no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Sag Harbor no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Sag Harbor- 'Travels with Charley' truck no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - John and Angel (dog) 1965, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - John, Elain, Thom, and John Jr. no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Angel (Dog) no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Elaine, John Jr. and Blake at Steinbeck House, ca. 1970-75 no date, photograph(s) (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Pacific Grove cottage misc no date, photograph(s) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Salinas Steinbeck house no date, photograph(s) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Hollister house- Residence of John Adolphus Steinbeck no date, photograph(s) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Beth Steinbeck, misc. no date, photograph(s) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Esther Steinbeck, young no date, photograph(s) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Mary Steinbeck no date, photograph(s) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Esther's Watsonville house- including Thanksgiving photo album no date, photograph(s) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Eugene Ainsworth no date, photograph(s) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Salinas Library statue of John Steinbeck no date, photograph(s) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Cannery Row bronze bust dedication no date, photograph(s) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Hamilton 50th Anniversary no date, photograph(s) (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Hamilton Ireland house no date, photograph(s) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Steinbeck Family no date, photograph(s) (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous, Series 5
  - Scrapbook and notes 1865-1910 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    French Language, poems, literary newspaper clippings and religious notes.
  - Abstract of Property from the City of San Jose concerning land in Santa Clara. 9/10/1908 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - By Laws of Stock and Fruit Farmers Association. no date (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Articles of company and minutes.
  - Mason's Bible of John Ernst Steinbeck 1902 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Presented by The California Convention of Annointed High Pirests to John E. Steinbeck, Consecration, San Franscisco, April 15, 1902. Franklin St Day, Recorder
  - 1938 paperback edition of 'Of Mice and Men' 1938 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Title page drawings and inscription 'To Neale from George'
  - A French Reader, Aldrich and Foster 1923 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Inscribed: John E. Steinbeck Stanford University 1923, Encina Hall 32
  - Bound certificate from the Grand Lodge of Massachusetts no date (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Induction of John A. Steinbeck as Master Mason, 12th November ---- (Masonic Date)
- Scrapbook, Series 6
  - Scrapbook 1880-1906 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Scrapbook collection of various newspaper clippings and some photographs from approximately 1880 onwards. Incompelete. Unused materials collated in separate box.